"Microbiome Manipulation
with Oligomannate for Dementia"
In 2020 a remarkable
case report was published
entitled “Rapid improvement in
Alzheimer's disease symptoms
following fecal microbiota
transplantation: a case report.”
The FDA allows the use of fecal
transplants for the treatment
of recalcitrant infections
of a bad bug known as C diff.
Serendipitous improvements
following such transplants
across a range of conditions
have been reported,
including autism, baldness,
and multiple sclerosis.
The dementia report involved
an 82-year-old man with
a five-year history
of gradually declining
memory and cognition.
His Mini-Mental State
Examination score
was 20 (out of 30), indicating
mild cognitive impairment.
But two months after receiving a
fecal transplant from his wife
his score was 26, which is
considered normal cognition.
By month six post-transplant,
the patient achieved a near
perfect score of 29,
and he also reported
a marked improvement
in mood, social interaction,
and expressiveness.
The potential role
of gut flora in Alzheimer's
is not completely
out of left field.
Butyrate, which is
what our good gut bugs
produce when we eat fiber,
is absorbed from our colon
into our bloodstream
and can cross
the blood-brain barrier
and improve the memory
function of mice and rats.
In people, the microbiomes
of Alzheimer's patients
have been found to have
fewer good bugs-
butyrate-producing bugs-
and more bad bugs-
pro-inflammatory bugs.
One reason this
isn't just dismissed
as a simple consequence of
poorer (lower fiber) diets
is that mice
transplanted with stool
from an Alzheimer's patient
perform significantly worse
on cognitive tasks than
those fed fecal samples
from a non-demented individual.
Could it be that fecal
transplants actually help?
We'll find out soon, as a
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of fecal transplants
for Alzheimer's disease
is currently underway.
There have been
about two dozen studies
of prebiotics, probiotics,
and fermented
foods for cognition.
Most reported improvements
in certain specific tasks,
but the findings were
inconsistent such that, overall,
there was no significant
improvement in global cognition,
nor in any single
cognitive domain.
Of course, differences in dosing
and formulations make it hard
to draw conclusions from such
heterogeneous data points.
There was a randomized
double-blind
placebo-controlled
trial published
that purported to show a
significant improvement
in Mini-Mental
State Exam scores,
but the validity of the data
was later called into question.
Similar concerns
haunt oligomannate,
a prebiotic conditionally
approved to treat
mild-to-moderate Alzheimer's
disease in China in 2019.
Traditional Japanese
eating patterns
have been associated with
better cognitive function
in the elderly
and lower risk of dementia.
That was evidently the
inspiration to try oligomannate,
a prebiotic derived from
a type of brown seaweed,
on a mouse model
of Alzheimer's disease.
Cognition improved in the mice,
but a subsequent 24-week human
trial in Alzheimer's patients
failed to offer
a significant benefit.
Not to be discouraged,
the Shanghai Green Valley
Pharmaceutical Company,
the developers of oligomannate,
funded another human trial,
a 36-week multicenter,
randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of more than 800 patients
with mild-to-moderate
Alzheimer's dementia.
Significant improvements in
cognition were noted
starting within
four weeks in those
randomized to oligomannate
compared to placebo.
Based on that trial,
it went on sale in China
in December 2019
for about $500 a month.
Currently, oligomannate is not
marketed outside of China,
but a similar phase 3
clinical trial is underway
in North America with trial
completion expected in 2026.
A safety analysis found
that the overall incidence
of adverse reactions
did not differ significantly
between those getting
the active and placebo groups.
Tempering enthusiasm
is the shady history
of Shanghai Green Valley
Pharmaceutical Company,
accused of a "whirlpool
of & bribery and fraud"
for illegally marketing supposed
anti-cancer miracle drugs.
A leading Chinese academic
suggested oligomannate could
"become the largest fraud case
in China in the 21st century."
The lead developer
of oligomannate
joined hundreds of other
Chinese researchers
who have been accused
of data falsification,
though a Chinese Ministry
of Science and Technology
investigation
concluded that only
a "small amount of misused
pictures were found."